DC Oral History Collaborative Collection 180
People's Archive, MLK Library
- Series 3: Buzzard Point Oral History Project
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews
    - Thelma D. Jones Interview, 2017-09-26; dcpl_dcohc003_08.mp3
      Thelma is a passionate and life-long community advocate and retiree of the World Bank. She is a breast cancer survivor who has dedicated significant personal resources and time to helping others across the entire life cycle: from helping the youth of Southwest to become job ready through skills training and mentorship to starting the Thelma D. Jones Breast Cancer Fund to help reduce incidence and mortality of cancer. In this interview she describes her incredible achievements through local organizations and through her career at the World Bank and discusses challenges associated with ongoing development in Southwest DC.
      Thelma D. Jones discusses moving to Washington, DC and her time spent living in Southwest; her work with the World Bank and its summer jobs training program for youth; the history of the Southwest Neighborhood Assembly (SWNA) and her involvement with the organization and many of its task forces, especially the Youth Activities Task Force; the Southwest Neighborhood Small Area Plan; the creation and mission of the Thelma D. Jones Breast Cancer Fund; and changes and developments in the Southwest neighborhood.
    - Barbara Ehrlich Interview, 2017-09-28; dcpl_dcohc003_09.mp3
      Barbara is a 47-year resident of Southwest DC, coming to the area by way of Pennsylvania in a mid-life transition to public health work from teaching and working with the U.S. Army. She has been deeply involved in coordinating and planning large festivals along the Southwest waterfront and in establishing the Waterfront Village: a volunteer-driven organization dedicated to supporting senior members of the community in remaining in their homes as they age.
      Barbara Ehrlich discusses moving to Washington, DC and her time spent living in Southwest; her educational background and work experience, especially in Public Health; her involvement with local organizations and events such as the Southwest Neighborhood Assembly's Southwest Arts Festival Committee, the DC Arts Commission, the Washington Waterfront Association, and the National Cherry Blossom Festival; changes and developments in the neighborhood; and the concept of aging in place.
  - Sub-Series 2: Transcripts
    - Linda Brown Transcript, 2017-07-25; dcpl_dcohc003_01_tra.pdf
    - Carolyn Mitchell Transcript, 2017-08-07; dcpl_dcohc003_02_tra.pdf
    - Vanessa Ruffin-Colbert Transcript, 2017-08-22; dcpl_dcohc003_03_tra.pdf
    - Ryan Pierce Transcript, 2017-08-28; dcpl_dcohc003_04_tra.pdf
    - Brian Hamilton Transcript, 2017-09-06; dcpl_dcohc003_05_tra.pdf
    - Bruce Kellogg Transcript, 2017-09-19; dcpl_dcohc003_06_tra.pdf
    - David Ehrlich Transcript, 2017-09-25; dcpl_dcohc003_07_tra.pdf
    - Thelma D. Jones Transcript, 2017-09-26; dcpl_dcohc003_08_tra.pdf
    - Barbara Ehrlich Transcript, 2017-09-28; dcpl_dcohc003_09_tra.pdf
- Series 4: ARTS DC: CETA and the Arts in the District of Columbia 1977 – 1982
  ARTS DC was a CETA arts program that employed over 300 theater artists, musicians, painters, dancers, poets, and other artists and arts workers in over 100 District of Columbia theaters, dance companies, galleries, music ensembles, and other arts organizations from 1977 to 1982. Artists who were employed in ARTS DC-funded jobs reflect on their ARTS DC experience, how the ARTS DC job affected their artistic careers and lives, and the impact of the program on the DC arts community. Oral history is an ideal tool to connect the stories of individual artists with the larger historical narrative of the DC arts community and of federal support of arts employment going back to the Work Projects Administration of the 1930s, and to document how the District's use of federal CETA funds for arts employment was different from that of other cities. This project was created as part of the D.C. Oral History Collaborative, a citywide initiative to train community members in oral history skills, fund new and ongoing oral history projects, connect volunteers with oral history projects, and publicize existing oral history collections. The D.C. Oral History Collaborative is a project of D.C. Public Library, HumanitiesDC, and the Historical Society of Washington, D.C. Learn more about the DC Oral History Collaborative on the HumanitiesDC website.
  ARTS DC: CETA and the Arts in the District of Columbia 1977 – 1982 collection contains five audio interviews of ARTS DC artists. The interviews were conducted by Jonetta Rose Barras in 2017. Transcript and indexes are included for all interviews.
  Artists; Arts; Racism; Poets
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews
    - Anne Becker interview, 2017-10-06
      Born in Chicago, Illinois Anne Becker grew-up in the southern Maryland towns of Takoma Park and Silver Spring. She attended Beloit college to study anthropology. After a brief stint studying abroad in France she dropped out, finally finishing her education at Johns Hopkins. Her work and reading have made an impact on the DC poetry scene and beyond, as well as the work that she has done with some of the 20th centuries best loved poets as part of her work for the CETA funded program Watershed.
      Poet and CETA Arts DC participant, Anne Becker reflects on her life and work with some of the most celebrated poets of the later half of the 20th century, including work with June Jordan, Dennis Brutus, Shirley Kaufman and Nobel prize winners Joseph Brodsky and Czeslaw Milosz. She also speaks about her seventeen years at Watershed Foundation, the work site for Anne Becker's tenure as an Arts DC CETA participant, where she developed develop her own poetry, eventually becoming the poet laureate for Takoma Park, MD.
    - Lorenzo A. Calender II interview, 2017-11-02
      Lorenzo A. Calender II was born and raised in Southeast Washington, D.C., where he graduated from Ballou High School. His life and work have revolved around storytelling, including significant contributions to D.C. radio, youth empowerment, and preserving the art of storytelling.
      Storyteller Lorenzo A. Calender II speaks about how he came to fall in love with poetry and science fiction at an early age, his work with radio that led him to interview such notable figures as Nikki Giovanni and Stevie Wonder, his work with youth that exposed him to "the power of storytelling", as well as what led him to create the persona, master storyteller Baba-C. Lorenzo Calender was an early recipient of ARTS:DC CETA funding.
    - Sheila Crider interview, 2017-11-02
      Born in West Virginia, Sheila Crider moved to D.C. at 8 years old when her father got a job as a guard at the Department of Engraving. Sheila Crider grew up in a mixed income black community in Southeast Washington, D.C. A recipient of ARTS DC CETA funding, Sheila is an accomplished poet and visual artist.
      Sheila Crider reflects on her life in the arts. She speaks about growing up in Southeast Washington DC and falling in love with reading as a child. And reflects on how living in Washington, DC, and the black intellectual movements of the 1970s helped to share her literary works. Time abroad in the Peace Corps, switching from literary to visual arts while living in France, time as an apprentice in Japan, and jobs that she took early a supplementary income, such as 10 years posing as an model for artists at the Corcoran, are some of the other topics that she touches upon. Central to the narrative is her work as a founding member of "Free DC," and the ways that ARTS DC: CETA funding helped her to develop her career.
    - George Koch interview part 1, 2017-09-29
      George Koch was born and raised in a small town in Ohio, where he came of age in the 1950s. He was one of the first Americans to serve in the Peace Corps, and it's U.S. equivalent VISTA. He attended college at Bowling Green State University and worked in the federal government, where his position on his union's organizing committee led to him becoming active in the labor right and Anti-Vietnam War movement in the 1960s. Having a love for painting, in 1969, just as Washington, DC was reeling from riots that burned huge swaths of the city, George opened an art studio in Adams Morgan, and has been a prominent member of the Washington, DC arts community ever since.
      George Koch reflects on growing up in a family of German immigrants in a small Ohio town. He speaks about the influence of his time in the Peace Corps, in the VISTA program, and his time on the organizing committee of a union for federal employees, and how these came to influence his politics and outlook on life. George talks about how he then solidified his prominent role in the Washington, DC arts community when he opened a studio in Adams Morgan, a year after the 1968 riot that had left much of the city burned.
    - George Koch interview part 2, 2017-09-29
    - Rogelio Maxwell interview, 2017-10-28
      Rogelio Maxwell reflects on the different influences that he brings to his art, as well as his role in the development of Washington, DC's art scene in the 1970s and 80s and how he decided to turn his exhibits into multimedia art experiences. He speaks about learning the congas at a very young age and being quickly recognized for his artistic talents while growing up in Brooklyn. His life is changed when one of his professors at the School for Visual Arts in Brooklyn encourages to drop out of school and let life influence his art. He then moved to Washington DC where he would eventually open Hardart studio and became a recipient of ARTS DC: CETA funding. Rogelio Maxwell continues to make innovative mixed medium art to this day.
      Rogelio Maxwell was born in Panama City, Panama. When he turned nine his mother brought him to Brooklyn, NY, where he was raised, went to school, and eventually attended the college at the School of Visual Arts (SVA). Convinced that he needed to experience life in order to be an artist, he dropped out of art school and made his way to Washington, DC where he would eventually set up a studio. With a background in both visual arts and music, he would eventually combine the two to become a pioneer in the multimedia art that fuses different mediums.
  - Sub-Series 2: Transcripts
    - Anne Becker transcript, 2017-10-06
    - Lorenzo A. Calender II transcript, 2017-11-02
    - Sheila Crider transcript, 2017-11-02
    - George Koch transcript, 2017-09-29
    - Rogelio Maxwell transcript, 2017-10-28
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes
    - Anne Becker index, 2017-10-06
    - Lorenzo A. Calender II index, 2017-11-02
    - Sheila Crider index, 2017-11-02
    - George Koch index, 2017-09-29
    - Rogelio Maxwell index, 2017-10-28
- Series 6: Federal City College Oral History Project, 2018
  Federal City College was D.C.'s first four-year public college. Upon opening in 1968, it was flooded with eager students, including Vietnam veterans, men incarcerated at Lorton Prison, civil rights activists, and young single mothers, almost entirely working-class and African-American. As a brand-new college serving the disenfranchised people of D.C., FCC attracted faculty from all over the country. They included poet Gil Scott-Heron; C.L.R. James, perhaps the most important black Marxist of the 20th century; and civil rights activist James Garrett, who led the fight for Black Studies at San Francisco State University before helping found FCC. FCC only existed independently for eight years: in 1976, it was folded in with two other schools to create the University of the District of Columbia. But these were a fertile eight years in the city's history, encompassing the 1968 eruptions and aftermath, the civil rights organizing that led to Home Rule in 1974, and, in 1975, the launching of a city government that strove to bring progressive democracy to the place that was becoming known as Chocolate City. Students, faculty, and staff from FCC played key roles in all of this.
  This project documents the history of Federal City College (FCC), an experiment in public higher education for the people of Washington, D.C.
  College students; Political activists; Societies and clubs; African Americans; Student government; State universities and colleges
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2018
    - Lawrence Bradford interview, 2018-07-04; dcpl_dcohc006_01.wav
      Lawrence Bradford was born in 1944 in Washington, D.C. He attended J.O. Wilson Elementary School, St. Augustine Catholic School, Francis Junior High School, Bell Vocational High School, and Western High School. After graduating high school, Bradford was part of the first class of students to enter Federal City College in the fall of 1968. He majored in computer information, played on the basketball team, and was close with members of student government. Throughout this time, he was involved in community action work and organizing for racial equity. Bradford went on to work in computer programming and information sciences at Washington Technical Institute, and later at the University of the District of Columbia (UDC). He retired from UDC in the 1990s and has since been teaching hand dance,the official dance of Washington, D.C.
      Lawrence Bradford discusses his childhood growing up in Happy Hollow, Adams Morgan, Washingonton, D.C., early experiences with segregation, attending Federal City College (now the University of the District of Columbia) to study computer information, his campus extracurricular activities including basketball and student government, his involvement in community organizing for racial equality, his career at Washington Techinal Instiute and the University of the District of Columbia, and his post-retirment career as a hand dance instructor.
    - Howard Croft interview, 2018-07-17; dcpl_dcohc006_02.wav
      Howard Croft was born in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania in 1941. He attended Duquesne University in Pittsburgh, Pennslyvania where he was involved in civil rights organizing before earning a graduate degree at Columbia University in New York, New York. Croft moved to Washington, D.C. 1969 where he worked for different anti-poverty groups and taught in the community planning, development program, and later the urban studies program at Federal City College (now the University of the District of Columbia). He was very interested in encouraging experiential learning among students, and was involved with the Lorton Prison College Program. Croft helped found the faculty union at the University of the District of Columbia, and was involved in labor organizing city-wide. He left University of the District of Columbia in 1995 and went on to work for several different social justice and labor organizations, including the Service Employees International Union.
      Howard Croft discusses his childhood in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, attending Duquesne University and Columbia University, moving to Washington, D.C., involvement with anti-poverty groups and community organizing, his career as a professor at Federal City College (now the University of the Distoric of Columbia), his innovative and expereiment approach to education, his work with the Lorton Prison College Program, his work with faculty and city-wide unioniziation, and his work with the Service Employees International Union after leaving academics.
    - Raymond Henderson interview, 2018-07-02; dcpl_dcohc006_03.wav
      Raymond Henderson was born in 1948 in Washington, D.C., and grew up in different parts of the city, though mostly in Anacostia. He attended Our Lady of Perpetual Help Elementary School, Davis Elementary School, Plummer Elementary School, Sousa Junior High School, Kelly Miller Junior High School, Gordon Junior High School, and Cardozo Senior High School. In 1966 Henderson dropped out of high school, joined the Marine Corps, and was sent to fight in Vietnam. Upon his return, he earned his GED and enrolled in Federal City College (now the University of the District of Columbia) in 1970. Henderson developed a political consciousness while serving in Vietnam and became involved in student activism while at Federal City College. He was a writer and editor for the student newspapers, along with other movement newspapers, and founded a student organization, the Black Jaguars, modeled on the Black Panthers. Henderson was part of a delegation of black college students who visited Cuba in 1974, where they met with people involved in liberation movements all over the world. After graduating from Federal City College, where he majored in political science, Henderson studied for a masters degree in political science at Atlanta University in Atlanta, Georgia, where he focused on China. After struggles with post traumatic stress disorder and drug addiction, Henderson went back to graduate school for photography in 1996. Today he lives in Alexandria, Virginia, and works as a photographer.
      Raymond Henderson, a native of Washington, D.C., discusses his childhood mostly spent in the Anacostia neighborhood, attending different elementary and junior high schools before dropping out of high school to join the Marine Corps at the age of 17, his experiences during the Vietnam War, earning his GED and enrolling in Federal City College (now the University of the District of Columbia) to study political science, the evlution of his political conscieness and his involvment with student activistm and organization including forming the Black Leopards (a student group based on the Black Panthers), his contributions to student newspapers as a journalists and editor, his participation in a delegation of black college students who visited Cuba to participate in global liberation movement activism, his graduate studies focused on China at Atlanta University in Atlanta, Georgia, his struggles with post traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and drug addition, his return to graduate school to study photography, and his career as a photographer.
    - Jennifer Ragins interview part 1, 2018-07-06; dcpl_dcohc006_05_1.wav
      Jennifer Ragins was born in Washington, D.C. in 1950 and attended Martin Luther King, Jr. Elementary School, Bunker Hill Elementary School, Taft Junior High School, Bertie Backus Middle School, and Roosevelt Senior High School graduating in 1968. She was a member of the first class at Federal City College (now the University of the District of Columbia), enrolling in the fall of 1968. She majored in community planning and development. As a student Ragins worked on plans for the Shaw urban renewal project, among other experiential learning experiences. Ragins was a member of the first graduating class in 1972, and went on to receive a scholarship to earn a masters degree in social work (with a focus on community organizing) at Columbia University in New York, New York. Ragins has served her community through her career in city policy and planning, working for several different agencies and on many different projects.
      Jennifer Ragins, a native of Washington, D.C., discusses her childhood and how she was influenced by the curriculum at her schools, attending Federal City College (now the University fo the District of Columbia) as part of the first class, contributing to teh plans for the Shaw neighborhood uban renewal project, earning a scholarship to attend the Columbia Univsity Institute for Urban and Mintiory Education in New York, New York, the impact the diversity of the students at Columbia University had on her sutdies, her professional work with the city government of Washington, D.C., including public health and community planning, her work with Anacostic Economic Delvement Corporation and Development Corporation of Columbia Heights, her travels to Moscow, Russia to particpalte in the Nuclear Weapons Freeze Campaign, and reflections on the impact Federal City College had on her career.
      Conditions Governing Access
      This interview is accesible only with written permission from the narrator.
    - Jennifer Ragins interview part 2, 2018-07-06; dcpl_dcohc006_05_2.wav
      This transcript interview requires written permission from the narrator.
    - Vanella Crawford interview, 2018-07-11; dcpl_dcohc006_04.wav
      Vanella Crawford was born in Washington, D.C. in 1948. Her family lived in a public housing project in LeDroit Park until she was nine, at which point they moved to 16th Street and Monroe Street NW. She attended Lucretia Mott Elementary School, Garnet-Patterson Junior High School, and Cardozo Senior High School, graduating in 1965. Crawford attended Fisk University in Nashville, Tennessee, and returned to Washington, D.C. to enroll in Federal City College (now the University of the District of Columbia) when it opened in the fall of 1968. One of her most profound experiences at Federal City College was spending a semester traveling with other students in Europe and Africa. Crawford majored in social work and after graduation attended Howard University School of Social Work for a graduate degree. She went on to work as a therapist and counselor.
      Vanella Crawford, a native of Washington, D.C., discusses her family history, living in public housing before moving to the Columbia Height neighborhood, attending Fisk University in Nashville, Tennessee and then enrolling in the first class at Federal City College (now the University of the District of Columbia), her awakening the the catholic faith and political awareness, traveling to Europe and Africa as part of Experiments in International Living program, her family's concerns about perceived political radicilization, the community reaction to the asscination of Dr. Martin Luther Kin, Jr., faculty influences on her decision to study social work, attending the Howard University School of Social Work, her professional work as a therapist and counselor, and her insights on parenting and attending college as a parent.
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes and Transcripts
    - Lawrence Bradford interview index, 2018-07-04; dcpl_dcohc006_01_ind.pdf
    - Lawrence Bradford interview transcript, 2018-07-05; dcpl_dcohc006_01_tra.pdf
    - Howard Croft interview index, 2018-07-17; dcpl_dcohc006_02_ind.pdf
    - Howard Croft interview transcript, 2018-07-17; dcpl_dcohc006_02_tra.pdf
    - Raymond Henderson interview index, 2018-07-02; dcpl_dcohc006_03_ind.pdf
    - Raymond Henderson interview transcript, 2018-07-02; dcpl_dcohc006_03_tra.pdf
    - Jennifer Ragins interview index, 2018-07-06; dcpl_dcohc006_04_ind.pdf
    - Jennifer Ragins interview transcript part 1, 2018-07-06; dcpl_dcohc006_04_tra_1.pdf
    - Jennifer Ragins interview transcript part 2, 2018-07-06; dcpl_dcohc006_04_tra_2.pdf
    - Vanella Crawford interview index, 2018-07-11; dcpl_dcohc006_05_ind.pdf
    - Vanella Crawford interview transcript, 2018-07-11; dcpl_dcohc006_05_tra.pdf
- Series 7: Asian American Voices in the Making of Washington, D.C.'s Cultural Landscape Oral History Project, 2017-2018
  This project documents the stories of Asian American immigrant-entrepreneurs and restaurateurs in Washington, D.C. Despite their small population size (they are four percent of the District's total population), Asian American restaurateurs have played a critical role in shaping the culinary landscape in Washington D.C. even beyond the Chinatown in Ward 2 for several decades. Many American Chinese take-out restaurants have long permeated every corner in the District. With the recent development of foodie culture, Asian American restaurateurs are introducing their heritage cuisines, diversifying Washingtonians' palates. The cultural and commercial practices of the food industry function as a valuable lens for understanding struggles and adjustments of Asian American small business owners in D.C.
  Asian Americans; Cooking; Family-owned business enterprises; Immigrants; Restaurateurs; Chefs